Guide to the New-York Historical Society Library Department Records 1815-2018 NYHS-RG 21
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV. Librarian & Curatorial Files, 1959-2013; 31.21 Linear feet
  - Jean Ashton II Files. Set 2 (4 of 11 boxes), 2003-2012 (Offsite-box 164, Folder 1-23)
    Includes files on acquisitions, general collection policies, and grants (e.g. Delmas, Mellon, Irene Diamond, Pine Tree).
  - Jean Ashton II Files. Set 2 (5 of 11 boxes), 2006-2011 (Offsite-box 165, Folder 1-22)
    Includes grants (NEH, NHPRC, and New York State) and budgets.
  - Jean Ashton II Files. Set 2 (6 of 11 boxes), 2009-2012 (Offsite-box 166, Folder 1-19)
    Includes exhibition files (including among others, Santa Claus, Malcolm X, Stamp Act, Founders Collection, WWII) and files on Alexander Street Press (digitization of Civil War material).
  - Jean Ashton II Files. Set 2 (7 of 11 boxes), 2003-2012 (Offsite-box 167, Folder 1-18)
    Includes project files (including Children's Aid society processing, Columbia School of Journalism, Questions About New York trivia book), New York University service agreement, and digital projects (including Alexander Street Press and others).
  - Jean Ashton II Files. Set 2 (8 of 11 boxes), 2008-2012 (Offsite-box 168, Folder 1-9)
    Includes digitization files, EBSCO, and IRLA.
  - Jean Ashton II Files. Set 2 (9 of 11 boxes), 2006-2011 (Offsite-box 169, Folder 1-29)
    Includes library administration (goals, tours, ADA compliance) and planning (reading room design upgrade), and miscellaneous reference files.
  - Jean Ashton II Files. Set 2 (10 of 11 boxes), 2006-2012 (Offsite-box 170, Folder 1-37)
    Includes files on fellowships and book prizes.
  - Jean Ashton II Files. Set 2 (11 of 11 boxes), 2008-2012 (Offsite-box 171, Folder 1-6)
    Includes files concerning off-site storage.
- Series V. Exhibitions, 1969-2011 (bulk, 1992-2001); 7.75 Linear feet
  The series includes files concerning various installed and proposed exhibitions. These files are only those found as standalone records during processing; many other exhibition files found with curatorial and conservation lab records remain with those series. Principal exhibitions represented in this series are actual and proposed "Library Treasures" shows from 1969-1995, Letters from a War (1993-1994) and the related Pray for Me (2000), Militant Metropolis: New York City and the Spanish-American War (1998), and Inventing the Skyline: The Architecture of Cass Gilbert (2000). The series also holds many original exhibition labels, though most are not identified as to which exhibition they were part of.
  The exhibition files are presented first, in chronological order, followed by the boxes of exhibition labels.
  - General Exhibitions File, 1980s (Offsite-box 179, Folder 1)
  - Blizzard of '88, 1988 (Offsite-box 179, Folder 2)
  - George Washington in New York, 1989 (Offsite-box 179, Folder 3)
    Includes bound exhibition text only.
  - Library Treasures / Treasury of the Past (1 of 2 boxes), 1969-1991 (Offsite-box 177, Folder 1-10)
    These two boxes include documents related to N-YHS's 1995 exhibition Treasury of the Past and predecessor exhibitions (actual and proposed) that had a similar thematic underpinning. This first box includes the checklist for the 1969 exhibition Treasures of Americana from the Library of the N-YHS, a checklist from a 1971-1972 "manuscripts show," documents related to the 1984 Treasures of Manuscript Americana, and principally files on selections for a proposed Library Treasures exhibition (circa 1991) that was not installed.
  - Library Treasures / Treasury of the Past (2 of 2 boxes), 1994-1996 (Offsite-box 178, Folder 1-6)
  - Letters from a War / Pray for Me (23 folders), 1992-2000 (Offsite-box 176, Folder 1-23)
    Includes the files of, principally, curator Margaret Heilbrun concerning two related exhibitions: Letters from a War, held at New York University in 1993-94, and Pray for Me, an extended version of Letters, held at N-YHS in 2000.
  - Navy Signal Books, 1992 (Offsite-box 179, Folder 4)
  - Curators Lab exhibition (proposed), 1993 (Offsite-box 179, Folder 5)
  - Creating American Cultural Heroes (proposed), 1993 (Offsite-box 179, Folder 6)
  - Edith Wharton / Age of Innocence, 1993 (Offsite-box 179, Folder 7)
  - Clement Clarke Moore, 1995 (Offsite-box 179, Folder 8)
  - Becoming Eleanor Roosevelt: The Early New York Years, 1996 (Offsite-box 179, Folder 9)
  - New York's Independence Day, 1996 (Offsite-box 179, Folder 10)
  - Presidential Politics: Election Year Documents, 1996 (Offsite-box 179, Folder 11)
  - Negative Politics (not installed), 1996 (Offsite-box 179, Folder 12)
  - Robert Fulton (2 folders), 1996 (Offsite-box 179, Folder 13-14)
  - Audubon, 1997 (Offsite-box 180, Folder 1)
  - To Hell with Reform: The Race to Become Mayor of Greater New York, 1997 (Offsite-box 180, Folder 2)
  - Love Letters (2 folders), 1997 (Offsite-box 180, Folder 3-4)
  - Henry James (3 folders), 1997 (Offsite-box 180, Folder 5-7)
  - William Sidney Mount, 1998 (Offsite-box 180, Folder 8)
  - Militant Metropolis: New York City and the Spanish-American War (4 folders), 1998 (Offsite-box 180, Folder 9-12)
  - New York City Police, 1998 (Offsite-box 181, Folder 1)
  - George Washington: A Man of His Time, A Man for All Times (3 folders), 1998 (Offsite-box 181, Folder 2-4)
  - John Genin / American Institute, 1998 (Offsite-box 181, Folder 5)
  - General Exhibitions File, 1999-2001 (Offsite-box 181, Folder 6)
    Includes schedules and proposals.
  - Inventing the Skyline: The Architecture of Cass Gilbert (1 of 4 boxes), 1992-1994, 1999-2000 (Offsite-box 172, Folder 1-23)
    These four boxes include files concerning the exhibition and catalogue for Inventing the Skyline. In large part, they appear to be those of exhibition curator and catalogue editor Margaret Heilbrun. Most of the documents relate to the catalogue but exhibition material can be found in the first two boxes.
  - Inventing the Skyline: The Architecture of Cass Gilbert (2 of 4 boxes), 2000 (Offsite-box 173, Folder 1-9)
    Includes color slides of the exhibition and actual labels. Also includes photographs used in the catalogue.
  - Inventing the Skyline: The Architecture of Cass Gilbert (3 of 4 boxes), 1997-2000 (Offsite-box 174, Folder 1-13)
    Includes correspondence related to the production of the catalogue and drafts of the text. (Later drafts, especially those from the copy editor and print proofs, were discarded by the processing archivist.)
  - Inventing the Skyline: The Architecture of Cass Gilbert (4 of 4 boxes), 1999-2000 (Offsite-box 175, Folder 1-12)
    Includes drafts of catalogue text, photographs and floppy disks from the essay authors with their submissions.
  - 75 Years of Holiday Magic: Macy's Thanksgiving Day Parade, 2001 (Offsite-box 181, Folder 7)
  - The British in New York Since 1770, 2001 (Offsite-box 181, Folder 8)
  - The Literature of the Lewis and Clark Expedition (proposed), 2003 (Offsite-box 181, Folder 9)
    Traveling expedition proposed to N-YHS by Lewis & Clark College.
  - John Lansing, 2011 (Offsite-box 181, Folder 10)
  - Exhibition Labels (1 of 4 boxes), circa 1995-2004 (Offsite-box 182, Folder -)
    These four boxes include original labels, some associated with identified exhibitions, others not. Identified exhibitions in this box include: George Washington: A Man of His Time (1998), Letters from a War (1992), Erskine-DeWitt Maps, First Ladies (2004), Abraham Lincoln Selections, Treasures Show (1984), and possibly Treasury of the Past (1995).
  - Exhibition Labels (2 of 4 boxes), 1970s? (Offsite-box 183, Folder -)
    Includes no specifically identified exhibition.
  - Exhibition Labels (3 of 4 boxes), circa 1995-2005 (Offsite-box 184, Folder -)
    Identified exhibitions in this box include: Presidential Manuscripts, possibly Clement C. Moore (1995), Cass Gilbert (2005), possibly Treasury of the Past (1995), possibly Robert Fulton.
  - Exhibition Labels (4 of 4 boxes), Undated (Offsite-box 185, Folder -)
  - Exhibition Files (17 folders), 1973-2006 (Offsite-box 358)
    Most of these files were transfered to the Archives in 2021 by long-time N-YHS librarian Mariam Touba. Exhibitions include Treasury of the Past, Evacuation Day, Greetings f the Year, blizzard of '88, First in the Hearts, Ardent Spirits and Demon Rum, To the Publick, Militant Metropolis Suspicious Truths, Thomas Paine, Independence and its Enemies. Also, here is a docent resource manual for Without Sanctuary.
- Series VI. Outgoing Loans, 1960-1992 (bulk, 1979-1992); 1.83 Linear feet
  The series includes records of library items loaned to other institutions. (Other records of loans can be found in other series, especially Series VIII. Department of Prints, Photographs and Architecture (PPAC, a/k/a Print Room) and Series IX. Conservation.)
  The files are in two sets, following original order: loans to 1985 and loans 1985-1992. The loans to 1985 are in chronological order and the subsequent set is in alphabetical order by borrowing institution.
  - Loans, 1978-1982 (6 folders), 1960-1983 (Offsite-box 186, Folder 1-6)
  - Loans, Art Institute of Chicago, 1981-1983 (Offsite-box 186, Folder 7)
  - Loans, 1983-1985 (6 folders), 1983-1986 (Offsite-box 187, Folder 1-6)
  - Loans, A-B (7 folders), 1986-1988 (Offsite-box 187, Folder 7-13)
    Includes Abigail Adams Smith Museum, Albany Institute, Amon Carter Museum, Anacostia Neighborhood Museum, Bard College, Brooklyn Historical, Brooklyn Musum.
  - Loans, B-L (26 folders), 1985-1992 (Offsite-box 188, Folder 1-26)
    Includes Bronx Museum, Chicago Historical, Columbia University, Cooper-Hewitt, Connecticut Historical, Corcoran, Erasmus Hall, Alice & Hamilton Fish Library, Fort Stanwix, Fraunces Tavern, Grey Art Gallery, Grolier Club, Herbert Hoover Library, Historical Society of Delaware, Hudson River Museum, Huntington, International Museum of Photography, Jordan-Volpe, Library of Congress.
  - Loans, M-Y (41 folders), 1985-1992 (Offsite-box 189, Folder 1-41)
    Includes Metropolitan Museum of Art, Museum of the City of New York, Museum of Fine Arts Boston, Museum of Fine Arts Houston, Museum of Brooklyn, National Archives, National Gallery of Art, National Portrait Gallery, New Jersey State Museum, New York Public Library, Operation Sail, Parrish Art Museum, The Octagon, Philadelphia Maritime, JP Morgan Library, Queens Museum, Rainbow Room, South Street Seaport, Tiffany & Co., Timken Art Gallery, US Senate Commission, Utah Museum, Valentine Museum,Vassar, Washington State Capitol Museum, Williams College, Yeshiva University Museum.
- Series VII. Board Library Committee Matters (RESTRICTED), 1950-2019; 11.25 Linear feet
  The series includes Library management's copies of Board of Trustee meeting materials, principally those of the Library Committee. The series also holds the Library's work files and other underlying material prepared in support of Board and Board Committee deliberations. As of 2017, only Library Committee reports to 1959 are open for research. See the Access Restrictions note.
  N-YHS generally restricts the records of the Board and the Executive Office for fifty years following the conclusion of the tenure of a President and CEO (formerly, Director). Accordingly, only those few files in the series dating up to 1959 are open. Subsequent files relate to the tenure of James Heslin (1960-1982) and later administrations, and so are restricted until 2033 and later.
  - Subseries VII.A. Board & Committee Meetings, 1950-2019; 3.29 Linear feet
    - Library Committee Reports (7 folders) (RESTRICTED IN PART), 1950-1982 (Box 190, Folder 1-7)
      Folders for 1950-1959 are open. Foldes for 1960-1982 are restricted.
- Series VIII. Department of Prints, Photographs and Architecture (PPAC, a/k/a Print Room), 1940-2018 (bulk, 1970s-2013); 32.17 Linear feet
  Biographical/Historical Note
  Although prints, photographs and architectural plans have been collected at N-YHS since the nineteenth century, the institutional history of what is now known as the Department of Prints, Photographs and Architecture (PPAC) begins more recently, in 1939. In that year, N-YHS opened its newly expanded and renovated building on Central Park West. Within the larger space, a new room was designated the "Map and Print Room" to house the collection (which included photographs even though the word was absent from the "M&P" Room's title). More importantly, staff was hired and assigned to the care of these collections. At the same time, as the professional staff expanded throughout N-YHS, an organizational division developed between the Library and the Museum, each gaining its own head who reported to the chief executive officer, then called the Director. Prior to 1938, both branches of N-YHS's cultural resources reported to the Librarian. The Map and Print Room did not form a third branch, remaining within Library management.
  Over the following decades, the scope of the collections of the Map and Print Room evolved with institutional changes. Responsibility for architecture was added from the Manuscript Department while maps were transferred to the Reading Room. Drawings were transferred to the Museum while the Bella Landauer collection was added. Landauer's collection of business and advertising ephemera came to N-YHS in 1926. It too was housed in a separate room at Central Park West where Landauer continued to add to the collection and work on it as honorary curator until her death in 1960. By 1973, Wilson Duprey was no longer Curator of Maps and Prints, but simply Curator of Prints. Similarly, the Map and Print Room became known as the Print Room, a name that, although referring to a physical location, has stuck informally over time to refer to the print, photograph and architecture collections and staff more generally. Certainly, in the records of this series and the institutional records overall, reference to Print Room will be commonly found, as in the title of the 1983 Print Room Collection Guide, an unpublished in-house finding aid.
  The 1980s and 1990s, the years that are most extensively documented at present in this series, saw significant developments in the management of these collections. In terms of overall responsibility, in the early 1980s executive management considered transferring the Print Room collections from the Library to the Museum, but with no appetite for this within either department, the move did not take place. But this proved to be just a postponement as the transfer eventually did occur, in 1989. As part of a reorganization of N-YHS at that time, a number of functions were consolidated under the leadership of the new Museum Director, Holly Hotchner. With their transfer to the Museum, the Print Room collections and staff took on a new name, which remains today: the Department of Prints, Photographs and Architecture (PPAC).
  PPAC remained with the Museum only eight years, transferring back to the Library in 1998, where it remains today. Yet during that brief time, several important initiatives were implemented. In 1992, Helena Zinkham, a former curator of prints in PPAC, completed her work on a preliminary guide to the print, photograph and architecture collection. Initially only an in-house guide, funds were eventually raised for the publication of the Guide in 1997. Wendy Shadwell, who had been Curator of Prints since 1974, was joined by two additional experts, Mary Beth Betts as Curator of Architectural Collections (1990-1999) and Dale Neighbors as Curator of Photography (1987-1998). The extent of surveying and cataloging of the collections increased, as did exhibitions drawing on them, including McKim, Mead & White's New York (1991) and Building City Hall: Competition, Construction and Context (1992). With the shift of PPAC back to the Library in 1998, PPAC continued both in its traditional role of providing material in support of exhibitions mounted by the Museum and Library, as well as installing exhibitions based on its collections. And under the leadership of Marilyn Kushner, PPAC's Curator and Head since 2006, the department has moved beyond these boundaries, perhaps most notably in Dr. Kushner's curatorship of the landmark Armory Show at 100 exhibition and its related Internet-based resources.
  The Department of Prints, Photographs and Architecture (PPAC) series includes files maintained by the curators and directors of the department, commonly referred to in the records as the Print Room. These records principally concern exhibitions, both those curated by PPAC staff and those mounted by the museum and other library units to which PPAC contributed. The series also includes records of loans from the Print Room to other institutions. Also included are files concerning the collections (e.g., acquisitions, conservation, surveys, inventories, cataloging projects) and administrative matters (e.g., budgets, reports, memos, statistics).
  The Department of Prints, Photographs and Architecture series is organized in the following subseries:
  Subseries VIII.A. Curatorial & Administrative Files (1950s-2015)
  Subseries VIII.B. Exhibition Files (1940-2018)
  Subseries VIII.C. Loans (1984-2015)
  The exhibition files in subseries VIII.B are those that were maintained as standalone sets of files, or at least were found in that way during archival processing in 2016. Exhibition files found integrated with a curator's general files remain there and so can be found in subseries VIII.A.
  From 1989 to 1998 the Department of Prints, Photographs and Architecture (PPAC) was a unit of N-YHS's Museum Department, rather than the Library Department. Accordingly, records related to PPAC (also known as the Print Room) can be found in New-York Historical Society Museum Department records (NYHS-RG 20).
  - Subseries VIII.A. Curatorial & Administrative Files, 1950s-2015; 18 Linear feet in 40 boxes and two oversize folders
    This subseries includes files of the late twentieth and early twenty-first century curators and directors of the Department of Prints, Photographs and Architecture (PPAC), referred to commonly in the records and in the institution as the Print Room. Specifically, the subseries includes files of Curator of Prints Wendy Shadwell (1974-2002), Curator of Architecture Mary Beth Betts (1990-1999), Curators of Photographs Dale Neighbors (1987-1998) and Holly Hinman (1998-2004?), and Directors Pamela Dewey (1998-2000?) and Valerie Komor (2000-2003). The date ranges indicate the time the individual held the position, not necessarily the date range of the records held in their files. The records, although associated here with particular individuals, commonly hold documents from their predecessors and likely also include files of other individuals that mixed in over time.
    The files hold a range of materials concerning exhibitions, collections, conservation, and administrative matters. The container list provides summary descriptions for the principal subject content that is held within each box. The content can be further summarized as follows:
    Wendy Shadwell's files include the broadest range of materials over the longest period of time. These files include internal memos, statistics, monthly reports, planning documents, budgets, consultant reports, collection inventories, acquisition documentation, reference inquiries, presentations to school groups, and conservation matters. The acquisition documents include index cards maintained by Shadwell's predecessor with notes on donations from 1969-1974.
    Mary Beth Betts's files center on the architectural collections and primarily include her working files for several exhibitions, especially McKim, Mead & White's New York and Building City Hall: Competition, Construction and Context, which drew on the John McComb collection. Betts's files also include correspondence related to the architectural collections and grants, particularly for Cass Gilbert-related projects. Associated with Betts, though not directly attributed to her files in the container list, are cataloging worksheets for the McComb, Pollard, Davis and Cass Gilbert collections.
    Dale Neighbors's files also include exhibition-related material, especially related to the 1995 gallery re-opening Treasury of the Past. Various exhibition possibilities are documented here, including some material for the planning in the late 1990s of a rotation of core New York City history-themed exhibitions. Likely in connection with one of these possibilities is a set of mounted newspaper photograph clippings apparently from the 1950s-1970s and at least in part from a series "New York's Changing Scene." Some administrative files relevant to the photograph collections are found here, including grants, acquisition possibilities, planning, and facilities. In connection with this last subject, there are three oversize plans from architect Richard Jansen for the existing and planned lay-out of the Print Room (1990).
    Neighbors's files also hold documentation of two projects: Helena Zinkham's A Guide to Print, Photograph, Architectural and Ephemera Collections at N-YHS and consideration of creating a "daybook"/calendar with photographs and other images from the collections. The Zinkham records include correspondence, inventories, drafts, and other materials concerning the development of her unpublished preliminary Guide (1992) and the final published edition (1998).
    Files from Neighbors's successor, Holly Hinman, primarily include information on various then-active photographers, likely in connection with potential acquisitions or exhibition. Many of the files have color slides, photographic prints, or digital media of the photographers' works; the container list entry includes the names of those photographers with such media in the files. Also included in the subseries are files concerning various surveys of the collections of negatives.
    The Pamela Dewey and Valerie Komor files include grant proposals for conservation, digitization, and other matters; processing and project plans for cataloging and other description initiatives, including the monthly status reports for the Mellon-funded visual materials cataloging project; general correspondence and internal memos; collection descriptions, such as inventories, lists, surveys, counts, and acquisitions/donations; and administrative issues, such as the move of the Print Room to the 2nd floor. These files also include reports from the Mellon-funded studies on contemporary/contemporaneous collecting and information about the Landauer collection, such as the transfer of objects to the museum and a folder of clippings and original magazines with articles dating from the 1940s-70s, among other documents.
    The subseries also holds files concerning the "Here is New York" collection and, to a lesser extent, the 2007 exhibition of the same name.
    The subseries is arranged by curator/director files in roughly chronological order. Integrated into the arrangement at an appropriate spot based on chronology and subject are three subject files (architectural collection cataloging worksheets, negative collections surveys, and "Here is New York" collection).
    - Wendy Shadwell Files (1 of 6 boxes), 1964-1995 (Offsite-box 213, Folder 1-13)
      Includes files principally concerning statistics, monthly reports, goals, planning, and reports from advisers.
    - Wendy Shadwell Files (2 of 6 boxes), 1967-1996 (Offsite-box 214, Folder 1-11)
      Includes files principally concerning collections, including inventories, collection management, and reports from advisers.
    - Wendy Shadwell Files (3 of 6 boxes), 1978-1994 (Offsite-box 215, Folder 1-16)